Guide to the Jacob Gould Schurman papers, 1867-1942 [1986].
Schurman, Jacob Gould papers, 1867-1942 [1986].
- Series I. Correspondence, 1877-1942
  - Letterbooks (Outgoing Correspondence), 1889-1921 (Reel 8-47)
    - Feb. 19, 1900 to Nov. 28, 1900 (Volume 8, Reel 11)
    - Dec. 3, 1900 to June 19, 1901 (Volume 9, Reel 12)
    - June 21, 1901 to May 26, 1902 (Volume 10, Reel 12)
    - June 2, 1902 to Feb. 3, 1903 (Volume 11, Reel 13)
    - Feb. 5, 1903 to May 28, 1903 (Volume 12, Reel 13)
    - May 28, 1903 to Jan. 23, 1904 (Volume 13, Reel 14)
    - Jan. 25, 1904 to Aug. 9, 1904 (Volume 14, Reel 14)
    - Aug. 11, 1904 to Feb. 23, 1905 (Volume 15, Reel 15)
    - Feb. 26, 1905 to Oct. 26, 1905 (Volume 16, Reel 15)
    - Oct. 27, 1905 to Apr. 5, 1906 (Volume 17, Reel 16)
    - Apr. 5, 1906 to Dec. 17, 1906 (Volume 18, Reel 16)
    - Dec. 18, 1906 to May 14, 1907 (Volume 19, Reel 17)
    - May 15, 1907 to Dec. 19, 1907 (Volume 20, Reel 17)
    - Dec. 19, 1907 to Apr. 15, 1908 (Volume 21, Reel 18)
    - Apr. 16, 1908 to Nov. 30, 1908 (Volume 22, Reel 18)
    - Nov. 30, 1908 to Apr. 20, 1909 (Volume 23, Reel 19)
    - Apr. 21, 1909 to Dec. 13, 1909 (Volume 24, Reel 19)
    - Dec. 13, 1909 to Apr. 12, 1910 (Volume 25, Reel 20)
    - Apr. 14, 1910 to Nov. 21, 1910 (Volume 26, Reel 20)
    - Nov. 22, 1910 to Apr. 10, 1911 (Volume 27, Reel 21)
    - Apr. 11, 1911 to Oct. 23, 1911 (Volume 28, Reel 21)
    - Oct. 23, 1911 to Mar. 13, 1912 (Volume 29, Reel 22)
    - Mar. 14, 1912 to Nov. 11, 1912 (Volume 30, Reel 22)
    - Nov. 11, 1912 to Apr. 28, 1913 (Volume 31, Reel 23)
    - Apr. 29, 1913 to Dec. 6, 1913 (Volume 32, Reel 23)
    - Dec. 8, 1913 to Apr. 22, 1914 (Volume 33, Reel 24)
    - Apr. 22, 1914 to Oct. 21, 1914 (Volume 34, Reel 24)
    - Oct. 21, 1914 to Feb. 22, 1915 (Volume 35, Reel 25)
    - Feb. 23, 1915 to Oct. 4, 1915 (Volume 36, Reel 25)
    - Oct. 4, 1915 to Jan. 20, 1916 (Volume 37, Reel 26)
    - Jan. 20, 1916 to May 18, 1916 (Volume 38, Reel 26)
    - May 18, 1916 to Dec. 14, 1916 (Volume 39, Reel 27)
    - Dec. 5, 1916 to Apr. 7, 1917 (Volume 40, Reel 27)
    - Apr. 6, 1917 to Sept. 13, 1917 (Volume 41, Reel 28)
    - Sept. 13, 1917 to Jan. 30, 1918 (Volume 42, Reel 28)
    - Jan. 31, 1918 to June 14, 1918 (Volume 43, Reel 29)
    - June 14, 1918 to Jan. 21, 1919 (Volume 44, Reel 29)
    - Jan. 21, 1919 to Sept. 12, 1919 (Volume 45, Reel 30)
    - Sept. 13, 1919 to Mar. 19, 1920 (Volume 46, Reel 30)
    - Mar. 19, 1920 to Oct. 27, 1920 (Volume 47, Reel 31)
    - Oct. 28, 1920 to Apr. 5, 1921 (Volume 48, Reel 31)
    - Apr. 6, 1921 to July 9, 1921 (Volume 49, Reel 32)
    - July 11, 1921 to Oct. 19, 1921 (Volume 50, Reel 32)
    - June 23, 1894 to Feb. 20, 1897 (Volume 51, Reel 33)
    - Feb. 23, 1897 to Sept. 13, 1898 (Volume 52, Reel 33)
    - Sept. 15, 1898 to Nov. 19, 1899 (Volume 53, Reel 34)
    - Nov. 18, 1899 to Oct. 13, 1900 (Volume 54, Reel 34)
    - Oct. 15, 1900 to Aug. 31, 1901 (Volume 55, Reel 35)
    - Sept. 2, 1901 to Aug. 13, 1902 (Volume 56, Reel 35)
    - Aug. 13, 1902 to Apr. 28, 1903 (Volume 57, Reel 36)
    - Apr. 28, 1903 to Apr. 16, 1904 (Volume 58, Reel 36)
    - Apr. 20, 1904 to May 23, 1905 (Volume 59, Reel 37)
    - May 24, 1905 to June 5, 1906 (Volume 60, Reel 37)
    - June 6, 1906 to July 25, 1907 (Volume 61, Reel 38)
    - July 26, 1907 to July 20, 1908 (Volume 62, Reel 38)
    - July 21, 1908 to Apr. xx 1909 (Volume 63, Reel 39)
    - Aug. 20, 1908 to Dec. 18, 1908 (Volume 64, Reel 39)
    - Dec. 18, 1908 to Apr. 24, 1909 (Volume 65, Reel 40)
    - Apr. 26, 1909 to Sept. 27, 1909 (Volume 66, Reel 40)
    - Sept. 28, 1909 to Feb. 1, 1910 (Volume 67, Reel 41)
    - Feb. 1, 1910 to June 11, 1910 (Volume 68, Reel 41)
    - June 11, 1910 to Oct. 15, 1910 (Volume 69, Reel 42)
    - Oct. 15, 1910 to Feb. 9, 1911 (Volume 70, Reel 42)
    - Feb. 11, 1911 to May 19, 1911 (Volume 71, Reel 43)
    - May 19, 1911 to Sept. 14, 1911 (Volume 72, Reel 43)
    - Sept. 15, 1911 to Dec. 26, 1911 (Volume 73, Reel 44)
    - Dec. 26, 1911 to Apr. 15, 1912 (Volume 74, Reel 44)
    - Apr. 16, 1912 to Dec. 23, 1912 (Volume 75, Reel 45)
    - Dec. 24, 1912 to June 23, 1914 (Volume 76, Reel 45)
    - June 25, 1914 to Aug. 15, 1915 (Volume 77, Reel 46)
    - Aug. 14, 1915 to Dec. 5, 1917 (Volume 78, Reel 46)
    - Dec. 6, 1917 to Sept. 10, 1919 (Volume 79, Reel 47)
    - Sept. 11, 1919 to Oct. 21, 1921 (Volume 80, Reel 47)
  - Family Correspondence, 1877-1939 (Reel 53)
    The collection contains letters exchanged among several members of the Schurman family, and includes handwritten transcripts of nearly illegible handwriting. As Schurman and members of his family traveled throughout the world, letters home provide a narrative account of both family and professional developments.
    - JGS Letters to his children (originals), 1929-41
      - 24 Mar. 1929 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - 8 June 1929 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - 4 July 1929 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - 16 July 1929 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - 6 Oct. 1929 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - 19 Jan. 1930 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - 16 Apr. 1930 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - 8 Dec. 1931 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - 12 Jan. 1932 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - 12 Jan. 1932 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - 17 Jan. 1932 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - 7 June 1932 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - 8 Mar. 1933 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - 15 Jan. 1934 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - 8 Dec. 1936 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - 2 Jan. 1937 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - 12 Feb. 1937 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - 20 Mar. 1937 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - 29 Mar. 1937 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - 19 Apr. 1937 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - 30 Oct. 1937 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - 8 Nov. 1937 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - 16 Nov. 1937 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - 16 Nov. 1937 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - 7 Dec. 1937 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - n.d. 1937 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - 7 Apr. 1938 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - 27 May 1941 (Original) (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - JGS Letters to his children (Copies and transcripts), 1929-41
      - 24 Mar. 1929 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - 8 June 1929 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - 4 July 1929 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 20)
      - 16 July 1929 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 20)
      - 6 Oct. 1929 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 20)
      - 19 Jan. 1930 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 21)
      - 16 Apr. 1930 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 21)
      - 8 Dec. 1931 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 21)
      - 12 Jan. 1932 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 21)
      - 12 Jan. 1932 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 22)
      - 17 Jan. 1932 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 22)
      - 7 June 1932 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 22)
      - 8 Mar. 1933 (Transcript Only) (Box 16, Folder 22)
      - 15 Jan. 1934 (Transcript Only) (Box 16, Folder 23)
      - 8 Dec. 1936 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 24)
      - 2 Jan. 1937 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 25)
      - 12 Feb. 1937 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 25)
      - 20 Mar. 1937 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 25)
      - 29 Mar. 1937 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 25)
      - 19 Apr. 1937 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 26)
      - 30 Oct. 1937 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 26)
      - 8 Nov. 1937 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 26)
      - 16 Nov. 1937 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 26)
      - 16 Nov. 1937 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 27)
      - 7 Dec. 1937 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 27)
      - n.d. 1937 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 27)
      - 7 Apr. 1938 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 27)
      - 27 May 1941 (Transcript and Photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 27)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (originals)
      - 19 Mar. 1933 (Box 16, Folder 13)
      - 1 Dec. 1933 (Box 16, Folder 13)
      - 2 Jan. 1934 (Box 16, Folder 13)
      - 18 Feb. 1934 (Box 16, Folder 13)
      - 21 Apr. 1934 (Box 16, Folder 13)
      - 2 Apr. 1934 (Box 16, Folder 14)
      - 3 May 1934 (Box 16, Folder 14)
      - 13 Nov. 1935 (Box 16, Folder 14)
      - . 24 July 1939 (Box 16, Folder 14)
      - 15 Oct. n.d. (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Will, poems, memorial service program (Mrs. Jacob Gould Schurman) (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Photocopies. "Letters from Joe. Originals in possession of Joseph R. Schurman." 1917-1923 (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - "Kuebrich xeroxes" synopses. 1929-1934 (Box 16, Folder 29)
    - Transcripts and photocopies; "Aunt Doty's Letters" (Box 16, Folder 30-34)
    - Transcripts and photocopies; "Aunt Doty's Letters" 4 Feb. 1934 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Transcripts and photocopies; "Aunt Doty's Letters" 5 Feb. 1934 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Transcripts and photocopies; "Aunt Doty's Letters" 11 Mar. 1934 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Transcripts and photocopies; "Aunt Doty's Letters" 6 May 1934 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Transcripts and photocopies; "Aunt Doty's Letters" 6 May 1934 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Transcripts and photocopies; "Aunt Doty's Letters" 23 May 1934 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Transcripts and photocopies; "Aunt Doty's Letters" 19 June 1934 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Transcripts and photocopies; "Aunt Doty's Letters" 26 June 1934 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Transcripts and photocopies; "Aunt Doty's Letters" 8 Aug. 1934 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Transcripts and photocopies; "Aunt Doty's Letters" 20 Nov. 1934 (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Series II. Schurman Articles, Speeches, And Books, 1875-1941 (Reel 48-51)
  A collection of holographic, typescript, and printed versions of speeches delivered or published by Schurman, concerning the several themes of his career: religion and moral philosophy, education, and political developments in the Philippines, Japan, China, Greece, and Germany. The series includes many addresses and speeches given on campus during his presidency
  - The Acadia Athenaeum., 18751881 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - The Centenary Movement of Thought., 19 June 1889 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "The Fourth of July", 1891 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "Address to Students", 29 Sept. 1892 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Grounds of an Appeal to the State for Aid to Cornell University., 11 Nov. 1892 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Address to Students", 28 Sept. 1893 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Moral Obligation., 1894 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "Religion a Part of Liberal Culture" in The Cornell Era., 27 Jan. 1894 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Phi Beta Kappa talk., 27 Feb. 1894 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - "Some Unsolved Problems of Secondary Education" in The Schoolmasters' Association of New York And Vicinity., 1895 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "The Problem of the Book of Job" in The Bulletin., Jan. 1896 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "The Vocation of the Teacher" at the National Education Association, Jacksonville, Florida., 18 Feb. 1896 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Notes for address (Welcome to Students)., 24 Sept. 1896 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - "Cornell's Action Regarding the A. B. Degree" and "A Notable Debate" (with M. Stryker) in Journal of Pedagogy., Mar. 1897 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - "Kidd's thesis is the importance of religion...", ca. 1897 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - "Address to Students", 23 Sept. 1897 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - "President's Address", 23 Sept. 1897 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - "Address" in publication of the American Society of Civil Engineers., 24 Nov. 1897 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - "Notes for Address to Students", 22 Sept. 1898 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - "A Young Man's First Year in College" in The Intercollegian., Oct. 1898 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - "Socrates in the Symposium...", ca. 1899 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Draft Manuscript: "Proclamation: To the People of the Philippine Islands", 4 Apr. 1899 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Draft Typescript: "Proclamation: To the People of the Philippine Islands", 4 Apr. 1899 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - "Following my personal view of present situation..." (Philippines)., ca. 1 June1899 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - "Secret and Confidential. Following my personal views of the present situation..." (Philippines)., 3 June 1899 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - "The President suggests that you submit views....", 5 June 1899 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - "Address to Students", Sept. 1899 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - "Address to Students", 28 Sept. 1900 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - "Expansion" in publication of the Union League Club, Chicago., 22 Feb. 1900 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - "Address" in the University Records, Cornell University Medical College publication., 1901 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - "Address" at the Thirty-third Commencement., 1901 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - "The Work of Cornell University for Agriculture.", 19 Feb. 1902 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - "The Elective System and its Limits" in Regents Bulletin., 1902 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - "Fellow Graduates", 19 June 1902 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - "Oration" in the University of Colorado Bulletin., Nov. 1902 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - "State Education: Its Rise and Present Standing", 13 Dec. 1902 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - "Emerson's Influence on the Higher Thought of America", 25 May 1903 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - "Speech Delivered by Jacob Gould Schurman at the Kishineff Indignation Meeting, Carnegie Hall", 27 May 1903 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Speech at the Alumni Banquet., 17 June 1903 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Address to the graduating classes., 18 June 1903 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - "My own attitude on the subject..." in the Proceedings of the 17th Annual Convention of the Association of Colleges and Preparatory Schools of the Middle States and Maryland., 1903 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Notes of a talk to students on: "How to Study", 1903 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Talk on Benjamin Franklin., ca. 1903 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - "The Future of American Colleges", Dec. 1903 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - "Business and Government", 24 Jan. 1904 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - "Address" in the publication of the Joint Educational Committee of the Legislature., 9 Feb. 1904 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - "Changes in Our Higher Education", 11 Feb. 1904 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - "The Function in Education of Mathematics, Languages, and Sciences" in the publication of the Connecticut Association of Classical High School Teachers. Statement of Schurman before the Committee on Agriculture., 1904 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - "Speech" at the Banquet Given in Honor of the Board of Filipino Commissioners., 1904 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - "The last phenomenon to which I invite your attention...", 1904 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - "Abraham Lincoln - The Statesman", 12 Feb. 1904 (Box 8, Folder 12-13)
  - Lotos Club Dinner: "The distinguished guest [Sir Mortimer Durand] whom you honor...", 30 Jan. 1904 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - "The Bearing of a College Education", 16 Feb. 1904 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - "The True Elements of National Greatness", 13 Jan. 1904 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Talk on Herbert Spencer: "Darwin wrote in 1870...", 10 May 1904 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - "When a government has for a long time demonstrated its incapacity to maintain peace...", 25 May 1904 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - "At the close of the academic year...", 22 June 1904 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - "I congratulate the people of Watertown on securing such a beautiful library building...", 10 Nov. 1904 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - "Some Unsettled Problems of Public Policy", 19 Dec. 1904 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - "But it is in the building...", 1905 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - "The Christian Faith of Today", 5 Feb. 1905 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Address to the graduating classes., 22 June 1905 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - "Government Regulation of Railway Rates", 6 Feb. 1906 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - "Peace and Economy", 6 Feb. 1906 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - "Liberal Culture: Athenian and American", 10 Feb. 1906 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Address to the Cornell alumni of Buffalo., 24 Feb. 1906 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Remarks at reception of Imperial Chinese Commission., 8 Feb. 1906 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - "Reaction of Graduate Work on the Other Work of the University", 1906 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - "Opening Remarks" in the pamphlet of the Dedication of Goldwin Smith Hall., 19 June 1906 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Address at Commencement: "A life like Ezra Cornell's is a sane and stimulating...", 21 June 1906 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - "Conscience in Business", 19 Nov. 1906 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - "Speaking at a Cornell crew celebration tonight President Schurman said that he believed...", 5 Dec. 1906 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - "National Greatness", 28 Dec. 1906 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - "The physical training of our youth...", 28 Dec. 1906 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - "The Reaction of Graduate Work on the Other Work of the University" from the Journal of Proceedings and Addresses of the Conference of the Association of American Universities., 1907 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Debate transcript: "Individualism vs. Socialism", 20 Jan. 1907 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - "Some Present Day Problems", 22, 25 Feb. 1907 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - "The Civic Club have asked me to speak on the Public Utilities Bill...", 14 May 1907 (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Address at Commencement., 20 June 1907 (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Address on New York Day, Jamestown Exposition: "To Virginia, the oldest of our states...", 10 Oct. 1907 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Manuscript for Cooper Union talk: "Out of this movement of reform...", Nov. 1907 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Address at the Tennessee Society of New York., 7 Dec. 1907 (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - "Some Present Day Problems", 1907 (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - "Governor Hughes" from The Independent., 26 Dec. 1907 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - "Memoranda for the Use of Gov. H.", 24 Jan. 1908 (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Speech on the anti-racetrack gambling bill., 1908 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - Remarks at Commencement of the Cornell University Medical College., 10 June 1908 (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Notes: "Announcements; Besides Religion there is Politics...", 2 Oct. 1908 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - "Our National Outlook", 21 Nov. 1908 (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - "The Problem of Great Fortunes", 16 Dec. 1908 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - "The Development of Religious Thought" at Salt Lake City Tabernacle., 20 Dec. 1908 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Address to Alumni in Syracuse., 6 Feb. 1909 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - "Direct Primary Nominations", 5 Feb. 1909 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - "The Adaption of University Work to the Common Life of the People" in the Education Department Bulletin, University of the State of New York., 15 Mar. 1909 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Address delivered before the Judiciary Committee of the Assembly at Albany on Tuesday March 24, 1909, the so-called Vivisection Bills, by J. G. S.., 24 Mar. 1909 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - "Reducing the Cost of Living", 12 Apr. 1909 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - "Address" on the Anti-vivisection bills., Oct. 1909 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Greeting to His Excellency Joaquim Nabuco, the Brazilian Ambassador, on behalf of the Latin-American students of Cornell University., 24 Apr. 1909 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Address before the National Peace Congress., 2 May 1909 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Speech at Independence Day Banquet, American Chamber of Commerce in Paris., 3 June 1909 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Address at the National Association of State Universities., 8-9 Oct. 1909 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "Address" in the publication of the National Association of State Universities., Oct. 1909 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Notes: "Goodbye to Crane; Welcome to Students...", 1909 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - "A School for Sanitarians", 11 Nov. 1909 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Address to the Modern Language Association: "Cornell University has from the very beginning...", 28 Dec. 1909 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Talk at American Economic Association., 31 Dec. 1909 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - "The Relation of the University to the Medical School" in the American Medical Association Bulletin., 15 Jan. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Address before the New York State Agricultural Society: "There has been an immense awakening of interest in agriculture...", 19 Jan. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Address at the banquet of the Cornell University Club of New York City., 27 Jan. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - "Agriculture and Education", 7 Jan. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - "Agricultural Type of Civilization", 1 Feb. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Address at Phi Beta Kappa Club of Buffalo., 12 Feb. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - "Justice in Taxation", 12 Feb. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - "Numbers of Students: The growth of Cornell University has been little short of phenomenal...", 1910 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Address to New York Unitarian Club., 17 Mar. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - "Alluding to the death of Mark Twain...", 22 Apr. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - "The Rockefeller Foundation Bill", 22 Apr. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Remarks by Schurman at Memorial Service for Ross Gilmore Marvin., 24 Apr. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - "The Relation of the University to the Medical School", 16 Apr. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - "Jottings on the Tobacco Case", June 1910 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Partial typescript: "... indication or proof of a combination in restraint of trade...", 4 June 1910 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - "Progress in Medical Education", 15 June 1910 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Address to the graduating class: "Nationalism and Humanity" pertaining mainly to Goldwin Smith., 23 Apr. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - "Goldwin Smith's Service to Humanity" from The Westminster., 23 June 1910 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - "Progress in Medical Education", 15 June 1910 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - "The American System of Representative Government", 18 Aug. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Notes for a talk to students: "The Loneliness of Freshmen; Fraternities and Clubs", Sept. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Resolution prepared by Schurman at the State Convention: "We especially commend his reverence for the constitution...", Sept. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Address to students., 28 Sept. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - "The Growth and Prosperity of Rochester", 8 Oct. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - "Some Elements of Religious Progress" in the publication of the Dedication of the New Buildings of the Union Theological Seminary., Nov. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - "The New Nationalism", 4 Nov. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - "Religious Progress", 28 Nov. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - "Progressive Policies", 2 Dec. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - Address by Schurman to protest against Russia's treatment of United States passports., 6 Dec. 1911 (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - "Puritan Ideals: Progress and Reform", 22 Dec. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - "Address" in the publication of the New England Society of Pennsylvania., 22 Dec. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - "We especially commend his reverence for the constitution...", Dec. 1910 (Box 9, Folder 40)
  - "Agriculture and Education" in the publication of the New York State Fruit Growers' Association., 1910 (Box 9, Folder 41)
  - Address given on Founder's Day about Goldwin Smith (mostly taken from Smith's own Reminiscences), 11 Jan. 1911 (Box 9, Folder 42)
  - "Jefferson and Public Policies of To-day", 13 Apr. 1911 (Box 9, Folder 43)
  - "Jefferson and Public Policies of To-day", 13 Apr. 1911 (Box 9, Folder 44)
  - "Man Moral and Man Brutal", 23 Apr. 1911 (Box 9, Folder 45)
  - Speech at the banquet in honor of Governor Dix., 2 May 1911 (Box 9, Folder 46)
  - "Our 'Barbarous' Civilization", 22 June 1911 (Box 9, Folder 47)
  - Remarks at Seattle Commercial Club: "The decisions of the Supreme Court in the Standard Oil and Tobacco cases...", July 1911 (Box 9, Folder 48)
  - Speech to the Canadian Club, Winnipeg., 21 Aug. 1911 (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - Address to Students: "What are you here for...?", 28 Sept. 1911 (Box 9, Folder 50)